Guide to the Nathaniel Hawthorne Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Nathaniel Hawthorne Collection
1800-1919
YCAL MSS 204
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.71
(4 boxes) + 1 art
The Hawthorne collection contains correspondence, manuscripts, and personal papers documenting the life and work of Nathaniel Hawthorne. Series I, Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers. Correspondence consists of letters from Hawthorne to others, including the reverend George Ripley and the publisher Ticknor and Fields, as well as a third party letter from Hawthorne's son Julian. There is one corrected and bound holograph manuscript of Hawthorne's Doctor Grimshawe's Secret in the hand of Julian Hawthorne. Series II, Norman Holmes Pearson Gift, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Material. Hawthorne's outgoing correspondence is personal and professional in nature. Noteworthy correspondents include Hawthorne's daughter Una, English merchants Francis Bennoch and Henry Arthur Bright, Delia Bacon, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Franklin Pierce, Hiram Powers, and Charles Sumner. Incoming correspondence consists chiefly of letters from literary acquaintances, such as Mary Howitt, James Russell Lowell, Herman Melville, Donald Grant Mitchell, and William Wetmore Story. Writings includes several Hawthorne manuscripts and one holograph manuscript by Franklin Pierce. Other Material includes a commission for an armed ship bearing the signature of President John Adams. Series III, Material from Other Sources, is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Other Material. There are several letters from Hawthorne to others, including one to Horace Mann, and two engravings.
Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864
Pierce, Franklin, 1804-1869
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Nathaniel Hawthorne Collection was acquired through various gifts and purchases dating from 1911.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile material may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies and photographs for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or related to Nathaniel Hawthorne, acquired by the library from a variety of sources. The collection contains letters, manuscripts, personal papers, photographs, and objects, and spans the years 1800-1919.
The collection is housed in four boxes and organized into three series according to provenance: Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, Norman Holmes Pearson Gift, and Material from Other Sources. Boxes 3 and 4 contain Oversize and Restricted Fragile material respectively.
Series I, Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, housed in box 1, is organized into three small subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers. The correspondence consists of several outgoing letters from Hawthorne to others, including the Reverend George Ripley of Brook Farm and the publisher Ticknor and Fields. Letters to Ticknor and Fields concern, among other subjects, the acquisition of books and the publication of a biography. There is also one third party letter from Hawthorne's son Julian to Benjamin H. Ticknor. Writings consists of a corrected and bound holograph manuscript of Hawthorne's "Doctor Grimshawe's Secret" in the hand of Julian Hawthorne. Other Papers include two certificates and a check signed by Hawthorne.
Series II, Norman Holmes Pearson Gift, housed in boxes 1-2, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Material. The Correspondence subseries is subdivided for outgoing, incoming, and third party correspondence. Hawthorne's outgoing correspondence dates from 1845-1863 and includes both personal and business correspondence. There is business correspondence dating from Hawthorne's service as surveyor for the port of Salem, to James Miller, and from his service as consul at Liverpool. In the latter case, there are letters dating from the mid 1850s to English merchants Francis Bennoch and Henry Arthur Bright. Other noteworthy correspondents include Delia Bacon, Hawthorne's daughter Una, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow, Franklin Pierce, the sculptor Hiram Powers, and Charles Sumner. The brief ALS to Delia Bacon, dated October 6, 1856, mentions publication of her work, presumably her controversial Philosophy of the Plays of Shakspere Unfolded (1857).
Incoming correspondence consists predominantly of letters from literary acquaintances, including Mary Howitt, Longfellow, James Russell Lowell, Herman Melville, Donald Grant Mitchell, and William Wetmore Story. There are also letters from Rufus Choate and Robert Winthrop. In addition to correspondence from family members, including two folders of letters from Elizabeth to Una Hawthorne, dating from 1870-1876, there are single letters from Samuel T. Pickard and Thomas Buchanan Read in Third Party Correspondence.
The Writings subseries includes several pieces of writing by Hawthorne and one holograph manuscript by Franklin Pierce. The Hawthorne material consists of three holograph fragments, two excerpts in Hawthorne's hand, and a corrected holograph manuscript, entitled "Autumnal Characteristics," of reflections on life and activities outdoors. Pierce's undated essay, "Influence of Essay Writing on Taste," explores the merits of the essay, as a literary form, on matters of taste and morals in both England and America, with reference to the English writers Steele, Addison, and Shaftesbury.
Other Material includes printed ephemera, Hawthorne signatures, a plaster representation of Hawthorne, and a commission for an armed ship named the Herald, signed by President John Adams and dated 1800, which identifies Hawthorne as one of the ship's lieutenants.
Some Pearson gift material, primarily correspondence and manuscripts, is accompanied by vendor documentation such as correspondence, invoices, receipts, descriptions, transcriptions, wrappers and folders.
Series III, Material from Other Sources, is organized into subseries for Correspondence and Other Material. There are letters from Hawthorne to William Fowler and Horace Mann, as well as two engravings of Hawthorne.
Oversize material, housed in box 3, contains material from Series II-III. Restricted Fragile Papers are housed in box 4.
American literature -- 19th century; Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Plaques (flat objects) -- United States -- 19th century; Authors; Adams, John, 1735-1826; Bacon, Delia Salter, 1811-1859; Bennoch, Francis, 1812-1890; Bright, Henry Arthur, 1830-1884; Hawthorne, Julian, 1846-1934; Hawthorne, Nathaniel, 1804-1864; Hawthorne, Una, 1844-1877; Howitt, Mary (Mary Botham), 1799-1888; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Lowell, James Russell, 1819-1891; Mann, Horace, 1796-1859; Melville, Herman, 1819-1891; Mitchell, Donald Grant, 1822-1908; Pierce, Franklin, 1804-1869; Powers, Hiram, 1805-1873; Ripley, George, 1802-1880; Story, William Wetmore, 1819-1895; Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874; Ticknor and Fields
- Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, 1841-1882; Series I; 9
  Scope and Contents
  Gift of Owen Franklin Aldis, 1911
  Series I, Owen Franklin Aldis Gift, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Papers.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Nathaniel Hawthorne
      - [Farley, Frank?] (fragment), [1841?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Ripley, George, 1802-1880, 1846 Oct 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Snyder, Philip, 1862 Dep 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Ticknor and Fields, 1852-[62?] (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Unidentified, 1851 Nov 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Third-Party Correspondence
      - Hawthorne, Julian to Benjamin H. Ticknor
        Related Archival Materials note
        See: Writings, Box 1, folder 6
  - WRITINGS
    - Doctor Grimshawe's Secret, holograph manuscript, corrected and bound, in hand of Julian Hawthorne, [1882?] (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Includes preface, dated November 21st 1882," by JH, and letter, dated April 25, 1887, from JH to Benjamin H. Ticknor
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Port of Liverpool certificate for entry of mechandise signed by Hawthorne, 1857 Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Port of Salem certificate for entry of mechandise signed by Hawthorne, 1848 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Check signed by Hawthorne, 1863 Jan 7 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Norman Holmes Pearson Gift, Dates 1800-1919; Series II; 0.63; (1.5 boxes)
  Gift of Norman Holmes Pearson, n.d.
  Series II, Norman Holmes Pearson Gift, is organized into three subseries: Correspondence, Writings, and Other Material.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Nathaniel Hawthorne
      - Adams, J. H., 1845 Feb 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Bacon, [Delia Salter], 1856 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Bennett, Charles Edward, 1863 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Includes photograph of Hawthorne
      - [Bennoch, Francis], [1853], 1859 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Bright, Henry [Arthur], 1854-63 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - [Burchmore], Zach, 1853 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Burritt, William (fragment), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Cozzens, [Frederic S. (Frederic Swartwout)?], 1862 Apr 26 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Crosland, "Mrs." (fragment) (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Crossman, Andrew J., 1860 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        Includes clippings
      - [Curtis, G. W.], 1851 Apr 29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Fields, James Thomas
        See: Ticknor and Fields, Box 2, folder 37
      - Fry, Herbert, 1856-57 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Goodrich, William, 1852 Mar 24 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Harris, Addie A., [1863?], Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Hawthorne, Una, 1854-60, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
        Includes signatures
      - Herbert, T. H., 1857 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Heywood, [A. M.], 1854-57 (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Holbrook, A., 1846 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - James Monroe & Co., [ca. 1842] (Box 1, Folder 28)
      - Lenox, John M., 1851 Mar 18 (Box 1, Folder 29)
      - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1852 Oct 5 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Miller, James "Gen.", 1846 Sep 21 (Box 1, Folder 31)
        Includes enclosure with signature
      - Muspratt, Sheridan, 1855 [Jan 10?] (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - [O'Sullivan, Louis?], 1855 Nov 13 (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Pierce, [Franklin], 1859 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Powers, Hiram, 1858 May 16 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Sumner, Charles (1811-1874), 1852 Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Ticknor and Fields, 1850-64, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - United States. Consulate, 1854-56 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - [Wilding, J. B.?], 1860 Mar 7 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Woodman, Horatio, 1856 Sep 15 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Unidentified, 1851, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Letters to Nathaniel Hawthorne
      - Cass, Lewis
        See: United States. Dept. of State, Box 2, folder 54
      - Choate, Rufus, [1855?] Oct 9 (Box 2, Folder 42)
        Includes copy of letter in Hawthorne's hand
      - Curtis, G. W., 1863 Mar 24 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - Howitt, Mary, [1854 May 14] (Box 2, Folder 44)
      - Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1855 Apr 25 (Box 2, Folder 45)
        Includes typescript copies
      - Lowell, James Russell, 1857 Apr 23 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - Melville, Herman, [1852?] Jul 17 (Box 2, Folder 47)
      - Mitchell, Donald Grant, 1864 Jan 12 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Mitchell, Maria, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Motley, J. L., [1861 Jul 14] (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - Pierpont, John, 1857 Jul 16 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Story, [William Wetmore], 1860 Apr 15 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Sumner, Charles, 1861 Apr 16 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - United States. Dept. of State, 1857 Mar 6 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - Winthrop, Robert [Charles?], 1864 Feb 15 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Third Party Correspondence
      - To Henry Arthur Bright
        - Hawthorne, Julian, 1882-83 (Box 2, Folder 56)
        - Hawthorne, Sophia, 1859 (Box 2, Folder 57)
        - Hawthorne, Una, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
        - ----, Arnold, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
      - Other Third Party Correspondence
        - Badger, Ada S. to "Mr. Christy", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 60)
        - Hawthorne, Elizabeth to Una Hawthorne, 1870-76, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61-62)
        - Hawthorne, Sophia Peabody to "Misses Chase", n.d. (Box 2, Folder 63)
        - Hillard, G. S. to James R. Osgood and Company, 1873 Oct 20 (Box 2, Folder 64)
        - Page, H. A. to "My Dear Sir", 1877 Jul 25 (Box 2, Folder 65)
        - Peabody, Elizabeth Palmer (1804-1894) to William Logan Fisher, 1853 Jan 26 (Box 2, Folder 66)
        - Pickard, Samuel T. to Mary E. [Farnam?], 1919 Dec 19 (Box 2, Folder 67)
        - Read, Thomas Buchanan to [Ticknor?], 1860 Oct 25 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - WRITINGS
    - Writings of Nathaniel Hawthorne
      - The American Notebooks, holograph fragment, 1850 Feb 20 (Box 2, Folder 69)
      - "Autumnal Characteristics," holograph manuscript, corrected, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - ["I have a tail like a boa- constrictor..."], excerpt from The Chimera in Hawthorne's hand, 1858 Jul 28 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - ["Look ever to the..."], English proverb in Hathorne's hand, 1852 Dec 31 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - "Time's Portraiture," article, holograph fragment, [ca. 1853] (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - ["Valdarno today looks like the..."], diary fragment, holograph, [1858] Aug 14 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Writings of Others
      - Pierce, Franklin
        - "Influence of Essay Writing on Taste," essay, holograph, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - OTHER MATERIAL
    - Autograph manuscript fragment and signature (Box 2, Folder 76)
    - Commission for the Herald, signed by President John Adams and Secretary of State Timothy Pickering, 1800 Jan 22
    - Consular documents signed by Hawthorne, 1855-56 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Penmanship book, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Plaster plaque with portrait of Hawthorne by R. B. Goddard, 1894 (Box Art, Folder 79)
    - Printed certificate from Niagara Falls, 1832 Sep 28 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Rent agreement in unidentified hand (Box 2, Folder 81)
- Material from Other Sources, 1849-1851; Series III; 4
  Acquired by gift or purchase from various sources. Sources indicated on individual folders.
  Series III, Material from Other Sources, is organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Other Material.
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Letters from Nathaniel Hawthorne
      - Fowler, William, 1851 Mar 16 (Box 2, Folder 82)
      - Mann, Horace, 1849 Jun 26
      - Unidentified, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - OTHER MATERIAL
    - [Object moved to YCAL MSS 902] (Box 84)
    - Engraving of Hawthorne, n.d. (Box Art, Folder 85)
    - Reproduction of portrait of Hawthorne, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 86)
- Oversize, 1800-1854; 1.67; (1 box)
  - Letter from Hawthorne to United States Consulate (In Series II), 1854 Mar 24 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Commission for the Herald (In Series II) (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Letter from Hawthorne to Horace Mann (In Series III), 1849 Jun 26 (Box 3, Folder 89)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 9 (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Box 1, folder 14 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 4, Folder 92)
  - Box 2, folder 69 (Box 4, Folder 93)